hello thank you for being here welcome
this is a conversation with Eric Godsey
it's about love and truth and waking up
into our fate important topics I think I
think of course they have important
fucking topics and I think there's some
real generative parts of this dialogue
and so yeah I'm excited to share it with
you Eric someone that I've wanted to
have on the channel for a long time he
really is one of the top people that I
have wanted to engage in this kind of
dialogue with it's partly because we
share similar affinity for union
thinking it's also because of the
general sense of I get of how he shows
up to the world and shows up to
conversation and I respect it a lot he
also has a degree in cognitive
psychology and is of course interested
in philosophy and psychology more
broadly so we share you know an affinity
for that as well yeah I invite you to
take the time with this I think there's
some meaningful metaphors here I think
we advance you know our own intrigue and
understanding about these topics or at
least it felt that there was that
positive movement of understanding in
this dialogue and so I hope that that is
something that you get a lot of value
from
all right that's the click so I can line
that shit up Eric Godsey thank you for
joining me it's nice to bloody meet you
again this is I'm young yeah beautiful
and beautiful well man I feel like this
is a bit of a it's a bit of an
interesting moment because I've been
aware of you and what you've been
putting out there into the world for
probably god I don't know at least at
least three years that seems to come
into my mind since pretty close from the
beginning since you started the
individuation podcast and I think that
was just because we share a lot of you
find that by the way Mandy how'd you
find it I have no idea hmm
I have no idea you know it was one of
many things that I probably was
listening to and you know God it could
be I think there's something that who
knows might have been googling some
Union thing maybe yeah I think that's
probably what it was I probably typed in
individuation of some things like that
you're one of the only six people who do
that Yeah right
well that's a pretty interesting thing
to have in common to begin with so
before I say too much can you introduce
yourself and a little bit about what
you're about to me really and also and
also our listeners for sure um so I'm in
love with psychology my favorite angle
to look at psychology from is Jungian
psychology I got a degree in cognitive
psychology a Bachelors of Science I
thought about getting a PhD in clinical
psychology but I thought for about two
to three years after I graduated how
could I help the greatest number of
people and it came down to do I get a
PhD and sit in an office and help maybe
20 to 25 people a year or do I learn how
to run a company and then use the engine
of a company to put out products that I
think will genuinely help people
psychologies and I eventually picked the
second one and then it was about
learning how to fucking do that and
that's basically been what I've been
trying to do the last four or five years
right now I work out on it um I work for
Aubrey Markus on like his personal team
and I'm just reading and writing and
learning and trying to figure out how
the fuck to be a person the thing that
I'm most interested in is essentially
the stories that we tell ourselves and
what is the most adaptive story that a
human can tell themselves that's kind of
my big question that I'm asking myself
right so what is the most adaptive story
we can tell ourselves and do we tell
ourselves it or do we sort of we sort of
lever out and realize it after the fact
yeah my truth is I don't know what the
most adaptive story is that's something
that I'm going to attempt to seek my
entire life I do think that most of us
live the beginning of our lives
unconsciously expressing a story that we
put together as children and there's
this moment that can happen in maybe
your late teens or 20s or 30s where
there's this first moment of oh I've
been a zombie living out programs and
then it's from that point where you can
begin to look at like what are my
stories which are essentially what are
my programs what are my unconscious
beliefs about relationships and myself
in the world and money and achievement
and all that shit and do I want to
continue to live out the stories that I
put together as a seven year old or a
four year old or do I want to make new
stories and then it's about what's the
most effective way to make new stories
all right do we have a climb out of the
story making for sure um I think flow
states are one of the ways that we
escape our stories I think that bliss
moment between a lover's eyes where you
guys are making love like that's an
escape from the story doing any type of
good work truly I think it's flow States
and practicing awareness / meditation
those are the ways that we can
temporarily step out of the story so
it's that place between stimulus and
response to put it a slightly different
way it's that revolution of attachment
and detachment
it's presence the the thing the thing
that's interesting to me about that
though is that so in the moment of
experiencing that the lovers eyes let's
say making love there is just that and
you are flowing with it and there isn't
the grasping to make sense of what
you're doing from that maybe it go a
core story like or but it's not fair to
just obviously I'm lump the ego and
stories together because of course these
stories play out unconsciously and they
have a you know their wellspring is one
from a Union perspective you would
understand as being nested in in the in
the unconscious so so it's in the moment
of it we are we are we escaped the
requirement from attending to what the
outcome necessarily is or what the what
the story is but but it seems to me that
there's still so much like there's just
a cook could we not see that as just
living out a character just expressing a
character expressing a role purely for
that duration and then after the fact we
say well actually I was now I can wake
up again and I've seen that I was
actually engaging in another sort of
pattern in another sort of story with
someone and the analysis might come
later on so in that sense oh so the
analysis will rise only after the flow
state is over and then we can post hoc
story lines what it is that happened but
in the moment there was not a story but
I would agree with you that
fundamentally it seems to be that we are
acting out a character and that that
character is to a very large degree
beyond our ability to change but I do
think that we have a little bit of an
ability to change it and that little bit
of an ability to change it is more than
enough to give people meaning to help
people transform their lives and to make
the world a truly better place
but it's gonna be hard yeah but it's
gonna be fun yeah yeah that's beautiful
I think I've heard you mentioned once
and it's an idea that resonates with me
also this notion of waking up into our
fate and so you've just mentioned there
this idea we can change ourselves a
little bit to what degree do you
understand that as essentially and
evolving into who you are and playing a
sort of an active role in becoming
unfolding that nature that you might
metaphorically consider as a seed which
for Philips yeah one of the most
powerful ideas that recurs to me is that
I am simply burning away my bullshit so
I can wake up to my fate which is like
when I really think about what that
means that fucking chills me but the way
that I kind of see it is you come into
the world with a specific energy
signature and it's a coagulation of the
set of genes you got from both of your
parents the environment in which your
mom was creating you inside of her womb
and anything that she ate or did or felt
like affected like the primordial stuff
that made you and in like the moment
you're born it's like I do think just
like the oak seed is destined to be a
tree you are destined to be some
specific thing but just like a tree just
like a seed can be planted and rotten
soil and there's always bullshit around
you we aggregate years and years of
bullshit on top of whatever our being is
or whatever our destiny is whatever our
core essence is and then I think you
know your adulthood is basically show up
and do the fucking work of burning away
the parts of you that aren't real and
you know I think there's a quote by
Confucius and that you have two lives
and your second life starts when you
realize you only have one
and it's this idea that your first life
is the life that you don't even realize
you have you're just unconscious and
then I think we all have this moment and
it tends to happen around the early 20s
maybe early 30s where you're like whoa
whoa I am this is the first moment I've
ever been self reflective and I see what
I'm doing and I want to change it and I
want to be like we all have this idea of
the person that we know we could be all
of us and we know the things that we're
doing that aren't in alignment with that
part with that potential and I think the
way that I see it is you are in a river
and it is taking you somewhere you can
learn to swim or you can be floundering
and drowning and smacking people who are
around you and trying to dig your nails
into the side of the river and I think
that aligning with you know who you are
is to learn to swim or to really to
float you know like I think that that's
the grace moment is when you really just
ah this is what I am this is how I am in
this moment you know it's akin to
dancing yes yes I think that river
metaphor is is a beautiful one what
comes to mind is what kinds of floating
are there then we might have seems to me
our capacity to discern to pay attention
to orient more gracefully around
obstacles or dancing along with others
floating similarly something we can
develop and perhaps there are I wonder
if there's some sort of if there's maybe
too broad and that might be a bit too
bit too basic but if there's in some of
the psychedelic experiences I've had
some particularly powerful ones number
of years ago now maybe five or six years
ago that sparked a lot of
research a lot of time reflecting to try
and make sense of what occurred was a
particularly powerful about five and a
half gram of dried psilocybin they'll do
it right
yeah I'm along with though and there was
a bit of a progression up to that point
but I found the jump from like three and
a half grams to 5 grams very
considerable and I had done that quite a
few like quite a lot and it was as
though in the climax of it my experience
my capacity for coherence was reduced to
two modes of orientation one which we
could one that I used the word
confrontation to describe and the other
surrender and what's interesting is that
often people use the word surrender to
signify this going with the flow right
but it seemed to me also that there
might be a positive and negative way to
manifest each of these modes of
orientation because we've had times
where someone is manipulating someone
else and perhaps surrendering to that
flow is maybe not what's best for anyone
involved so how then do you hold your
back to it so the other ways to hold
your boundaries right so maybe this
maybe this confrontation is oh actually
like this log that's coming at me or
this these leaves there you go there are
some leaves in the in the stream I don't
need to orient around them that's no log
there's some leaves I'll just take them
I'll take those take the feeling of that
does that is that something that
resonates with you too to begin with two
broad modes of orientation in response
to what is effectively the appearance of
radical anomaly and novelty as we
ingress
so here's how I orient myself
because I admit that I am an eggnog ma
to myself which is a quote from young
how I get to know myself is I do my best
to admit to myself what my truth is in
this moment like what feels like my
truth so the two big things are
cultivate awareness there's all sorts of
practices that I can do to do that and
then to cultivate the courage to speak
and act my truth to myself and to others
and if I do that I will find where my
boundaries are I will find how to
respond to leave or to a log because the
truth is that each of us our
consciousness is resting inside of this
magical amazing incomprehensible thing
that you could get to know if you wanted
to and I think the way you get to know
what this thing is which is your your
nervous system I think is the pinnacle
of creation in the known universe you
know that we know of right now it's a
nervous system and you get to learn new
yours and I think the way you find
optimal Grace in this life is to figure
out what your truth is and truth might
be the wrong word but I think it if it
makes sense to most people when I ask
you what's your truth right now you know
I'm more than happy to use truth to
refer to that I mean we could I was just
writing yesterday about all the
different ways we can use truth language
is one of those things it's it's like
I'm not really so fussed about quibbling
with people to be honest with you I mean
sometimes there's a time for quibbling
right if you're sitting down to have an
analytic philosophical discussion it's
like no fuck you that's not how it going
to be using this word but but really
number of people I speak to coming from
all these different epistemic
backgrounds many people autodidact
others trained in certain schools of
thinking
it's just so many it's like there's a
way of relating to someone the
dialogical process is one way it's like
a translation of of that of the meaning
of the feeling ultimately of what
someone's trying to communicate
especially when it comes to what we're
talking about here which is something
about what it is like to show up
meaningfully to the world and to be in
some relationship with yourself and the
world
truth is I mean an authentic expression
at a realization of what is of what is
resonant real these kind of words are
what I get from how you're using the
word truth they're correct yeah but
there's something again that comes to
mind which is I'm interested to hear how
how you articulate the decision of
whether or not to speak or let the
energy let the images continue to
coalesce right because there's lots of
different truths I've got stuff popping
up all the time right but but but but it
keeping keeping you know I say I think
when we spoke on the phone you mentioned
the sort of a cultivation of competence
right something I've been trying to do
is like develop over the last number of
years it's not necessarily to jump on
exact on it you don't jump on every
tangent that comes along sometimes it's
you check in again so what comes up for
you there in terms of when when do you
express that truth versus when do you
let coalesce into something a little bit
more cultivated that's a great question
and the way that I think about it is do
I understand this well enough to express
it in love if I don't feel like I can
express it in love I'm not done
understanding it and so that's to myself
and to other people and the other part
of that question is it's kind of this
intuitive thing they to start by
speaking your truth and you will
probably be clumsy and people around you
are probably going to not respond to it
very well then you've got to start
the alternative is you're just lying
like dude come on early 20s really was
like 19 and 20 and 21 I was not in truth
with anyone who was around me and so
everyone around me that I called a
friend were really just people who drink
with me and there was no like authentic
like we could get drunk and laugh and
say that we loved each other but I knew
I wasn't connecting to them because I
wasn't in truth with myself and now like
all of my relationships are so much
deeper and it's it's it's a beautiful
thing when you cultivate that type of
connection with any of your friends like
I've been going through kind of an
emotional time this last week and I can
cry in front of all of my friends and
there's no like it's just I can see that
my crying gives them permission to cry
in the future I feel cathartic because
I'm not hiding something that feels true
and I love them because I see how they
respond when they see me in that state
and seven years ago I would have
pretended that I wasn't sad and I just
think that so many of us are not being
ourselves because we think that it's
wrong or we think that people won't
accept us and like what I find time and
time and time and time and time again is
anyone who is willing to show up in life
who isn't hiding from themselves they
respond so well to when when someone
speaks the truth and the thing that I
want to point out is all of us have this
ability to detect in another person they
just said something that was hard for
them to admit like we all have this
radar thing and it's so counterintuitive
but people are afraid to admit the
things that they're afraid to admit but
like people love you and admire you when
you do it the people who market are the
people who are terrified to do it for
themselves and those are the people who
will mark you and it's just like oh this
is someone who's afraid
yes yes that's beautiful well I'm really
glad to hear that that's an experience
you have in your life thank you
yeah here's something else I've been
battling with and it relates slightly
and I hear you by the way I I really
hear you let's consider someone take
myself we didn't have to think about
anyone else let's do that
let's say I'm a child they say I'm in my
teens I'm in my teens let's say I
haven't developed many of those
relationships yet I would say actually
in my case in fact I was developing
those relationships from a young age I
think this sort of showing up in truth
is something that perhaps because of
what occurred in my childhood was made
perhaps more necessary for me to develop
at a younger age but that's I mean it's
a continual process you know it's not so
much one pill of becoming aware it's a
constant it's a constant struggle right
there the capacity for delusion is it's
consistent it's continuous so it really
is a continual waking up process I think
that's really important to stress right
and but let's say I'm a teenager and I
have not developed that many of these
relationships am i inauthentic or am I
in fact merely authentic lyrics pressing
a less aware state of nature state of
experience I've been battling with this
word authenticity a little bit recently
it's been brought up to me and I've been
using it quite a lot it's like authentic
expressionist right showing up
authentically that even in the case of
the lie is this something that is
appropriate to say authentic or not
I think authenticity depends on
awareness and if you are 15 and you have
never had it modeled for you about how
to be courageous and speak your truth
and you're not speaking your truth I
wouldn't say that that person is
inauthentic I would say that that person
is 15 you know um for me like I look
back on when I was 18 and a bunch of
stuff happened where I must have been
depressed I must have been depressed but
I was so unconscious that I don't it
would be a lie to say that I remember
feeling depressed but like I lived alone
I had gotten rotator cuff surgery on my
shoulder I had to stop playing
basketball which was my entire life and
I was taking oxy coding every day and I
was eating and I gained like 40 pounds
over like eight months and I don't
remember being upset at all mmm but it's
because I felt like I was so fucking
unconscious and so what I would say is
that authenticity comes down to the
degree of awareness that the individual
has and nobody can make that claim for
anyone other than themselves and so you
are the supreme arbiter of whether or
not you're being authentic
you might feel justified to judge that
someone else is not and you might be
right some of the time but truly only
you can know your degree of authenticity
and I think that that is enough yes why
I I definitely agree with that is on
every individual to be the the measure
of themselves this is that divine right
I think we can argue quite strongly in
it it's not a matter for argument really
but it's interesting right because
of where I'm aiming and that's not to I
say where we aim we have to have goals
but also not to attach too hard right
man so so with that in mind part of
where I'm aiming is the development of
this sort of a character and presence
that can hold a certain space for the
authentic expression of others perhaps
in a very high-pressure situation
perhaps where it matters and I think it
always matters actually but I suppose
maybe some sometimes you feel the
moments upon you more than others and in
such situations it's difficult to
imagine not finding yourself in the
place of the judge right like if
someone's trying to manipulate you for
instance let's say it's like oh hang on
busy you mentioned before it's like you
feel when someone's showing up in a way
that's difficult for them but true and
so it sort of follows from that that
there's a sense we get when someone's
holding something back and that that
maybe is obvious someone so you're
talking to a friend or or a loving
partner and what have you and they begin
a sentence halfway and they trail off
because they get nervous it's like oh
I'm I want to know what's at the end of
that sentence that feels like something
that we should be talking about and
that's you know an obvious example but
but when when something's a little bit
more subtle cool like it's a these can
get zhem when do you see I'm not so
interested in calling someone out but we
do we do this social fucking thing it's
like no that was a misstep in the dance
like I really still love you the dance
continues but it's like I wonder can you
can you comment on that it's like it's
that like it's isn't because it is on
you to determine to be the measure of
your own authenticity but nevertheless
we still have to we have to fix things
in the world where we put down
boundaries that have an effect on others
and there has to be a way to
I mean you do that from your truth let's
say and if you're not doing it from that
then it's a puff you like I feel what
you're asking so the first thing that I
would say is you have a very specific
thing that you're talking about that
you're asking in a vague way but I will
answer the vague way back there yeah
the greatest power that we have
linguistically in the world is to ask a
good question mm-hmm so if you feel
anything weird and the other person
become and train yourself to be a master
at asking a genuine question and it
could be like hey I I feel this weird
energy in my chest when I hear that you
trail off at the end of that sentence
could you tell me what was there and
like the way you ask the question it can
completely shift the energy of the
entire thing
and like the way you ask the question is
energetically telling them should they
lie and hide or can they be comfortable
sharing whatever the uncomfortable thing
is yes that's the answer
yeah beautiful well have been some of
the hardest lessons you've learned along
the way to get to the point where you
feel competent to answer such a question
you know I don't know I think it really
comes down to in college just the way it
worked out is I would come home from
school my friends would be in the garage
smoking weed I would come in I'd start
smoking and they just started asking me
questions about what I learned that day
and I would just start to tell them what
I learned and then it just it just grew
into a thing where my friends asked me
questions and now with social media I
just let people ask me questions and
because my guiding ethos is to the best
of my ability speak and act my truth and
love like ask me anything and I I will
check in and I will feel what feels like
my limit of what the thing is then I'll
just fucking say it and I'll just do it
over and over and over and over and I
think what lets me feel qualified to
answer is that I think anyone is
qualified to answer when it's regarding
with their opinion is and so that's just
how I see it
anyone can talk yes why I agree with
that it's not so much a matter of of
qualification but I think you I feel
that that was very much an answer to my
question
it's interesting because I'm not exactly
I am looking for answers to questions I
suppose but really when I approached
these conversations and conversations in
general it's perhaps a little bit
different over video there's a there's a
bit of a time lag and I can't you know I
can't see the rest of your body and it's
a little there's something more
restrained about how we're doing this
thing and that's fine and as this sort
of incumbent life
falls back to me to move the
conversation on in ways where it's like
often when you're spending time with
someone it's just good to it's nice just
to stay silent for a bit this is perhaps
a limitation of podcasts sure which is
which is interesting isn't it and I
think that's something I might
experiment with a little bit in person
it's a little bit easier
to hold those moments of silence because
the energy can be held a little bit more
whereas if I was to discuss silent right
now and stay still you'd be like is he
freezing is he what like the quickness
of the voice coming back in would be
there but I might like to experiment
with that someday how do you find how do
you find podcasting in that in that
regard is is there or just filming
yourself in general there can be a real
and for me getting a bit better at it
but there is that flick it's like it's
not just you and me we are here right
now like I'm Jen you I am here with you
I'm here with your your pixelated face
but but there's a bunch of other people
here too in some sense and so whatever
persona I've developed to hold both the
other people and you is what I'm here
with also and I wonder what the effect
of that is when it comes to modeling
interaction and communication in general
there's a certain privacy that is that
is not so simple to bring to bear even
when you're pushing yourself for it
what's so a question out of this might
be something like mmm that is quite
personal you don't have to answer it
where are you when you are most private
with yourself
probably when I'm looking in my eye in
the mirror and maybe when I'm
[Music]
envisioning something when I'm laying in
bed at night
that's probably my most private moments
mm-hmm like I really feel like there's a
God inside of me that is a reflection of
whatever the total Spirit is that is my
potential like that is at the edge of
time and I feel it's inside of me and
when I need help when I feel lost or
when I just want to give thanks I'll
fuckin talk to that thing and I feel
like those moments is when I'm most
private
I saw of communion with higher self
exactly yeah
I've heard you mentioned thank you for
sharing that I've heard you mention I'd
and I as well I should say I'm I
wouldn't ask you anything I'm not
willing to speak on myself yeah I would
love to hear your answer for sure I
think it's something very similar III
think it it's any mode of expression
where where you are in touch with your
nature there's a and a nakedness to the
second nakedness but a fullness I had an
experience the other day and actually
don't know this is something for me that
to express this is like wow maybe maybe
I shouldn't and so I was the best one
yeah well I'm gonna Pat it a little bit
I'm gonna Pat it a little bit but I'm
because it's like I mean it relates to
this notion of of contemplating or being
with higher self in fact this particular
experience was I've done met different
meditative practices before where it's
like imagine yourself in five years
times like an older brother you're
holding yourself you can take you can
take yourself on the shoulder and give
you that little bit of a smile and that
sort of knowing look of you've got this
all right yeah I know it's tough I know
it's difficult I know you're confused
but you have it you have that you have
that fire in you you will you got it
mate it's all good and then it's like
all right how about an image of that
five years 10 years 15 years 20 years 5
years ago 10 years ago and all its
different manifestations of what you
could be and then were image coalesce is
all of those together sort of an image
of the the confluence of these that is
somehow it's it's a it's a self that
transcends all of them across all
possible manifestations is the
you'll form and you know maybe I won't
say just yet exactly how that image
appears to me but that image is there
and it reminds me of of what you what
you mention here there's something
there's a there's a capacity to check in
and it is a sort of loving truth it is a
sort of that it's a sort of affirmation
of the potential and possibility and
wonder of life as much as it is a an
inclusion and and acceptance of the
suffering and the difficulty but an
affirmation nevertheless and there's
something to tap into can be with it
it's like how do you read what is the
mechanism by which yuria tend when
you're dropped into the ocean I would
say it's these moments of stepping into
novelty it's that creative space of
stepping over the boundary
perhaps there perhaps there you perhaps
there it's um it's a it's a moment of
reckoning perhaps these are perhaps this
is the most private moment for me well I
mean it's something I wasn't willing to
precisely share as much as I could and I
would with you just individually so but
but this but this brings something up
else to me as well and I think perhaps
you can help me with this it's like I've
mentioned it a few times on the podcast
before and in different ways so when we
are speaking our truth okay there's a
container that forms between us and I
can trust you to hold that but when the
content and then maybe the containers
never totally set maybe I don't ever
totally know and there is that faith in
it in trusting being held when you are
speaking to many others when you are in
a place where you're not so sure there's
a sense in which there is more at stake
right there's an expression don't cast
pearls before swine
right there's a sort sort of you know if
if if what you if what you put out there
is not held maybe it's being eaten a
little bit maybe your energy is being
taken somehow and I'm sure
I wonder what comes up for you then yeah
um a distinction between because it is
my truth does not mean it must be shared
and my truth could be right now I feel
that if I gave you know this audience
advice it would not be accepted and so
I'm gonna choose not to share it that
would be my truth in that moment so
simply because it is thought does not
mean that it must be expressed and for
example like if someone tells me a
secret but somebody else asks me did X
do why my truth is I'm I would feel
wrong being a part of this conversation
between you two I think you should go
talk to them you know like so truth does
not mean it must be divulged and that's
why I think there's endless nuance
inside of us as we cultivate more
awareness and you can start to feel the
shades and the different hues around
your feelings and the truth might be
something like I don't feel that I am
yet able to articulate this in truth and
so I'm going to think about it for a
couple of days and I will get back to
you you know like all of those are
examples of how you can speak your truth
in the moment it doesn't mean that you
have to give birth to a child that's not
ready yeah beautiful so that is and god
I feel that is a that is a constant less
than a constant practice to learn and
it's one that in some sense as well it's
like God you do all the preparation you
want but it's like eventually you're
still stepping out there you're still
stepping out into the unknown and this
is that this is the paradox you in some
sense for all the preparation
it's not a knowing in advance
necessarily right so it's the
cultivation of a toolkit absolutely men
like I spent a lot of my life
preparing for life and now I feel like a
lot of my life is living life and I'm
grateful for the tools but you still
gotta fucking feel the fields and go
through the things and the trials and
the fire and nothing is going to hone
you like the actual experiences yeah
books or Maps mm-hmm experiences or the
forest mm-hmm yeah beautiful
I find this well that I mean it's the
it's the practice of your own expression
so I do read you know I've read a bit
but but to be honest with you I find
that if I'm not I feel it's the working
through it's the it's the expression
through of the ideas its cultivating my
own interest actually that I doing most
of the learning and and the teaching in
this way I mean up not getting facts
from other places but in terms of in
terms of developing the scaffolding your
concerns will framework but then also
the link between the concept and the
feeling this is the really difficult
thing about young to grasp I think for
many people it's like someone could ask
me okay what's what's an archetype how
do we understand that it's like a sort
of like Plato's forms or something like
this but it's not quite that and it's
like well one of the challenging things
is that it and maybe this is why it mean
it's a young'uns do psychotherapy right
there's a there's the concept but then
there's its manifestation in your actual
life right there's the living out of
that archetype and in some sense if
you're not in touch with the lived
reality of it it can begin to name these
different energetic confluences as they
are relevant to the narrative and
ongoing narrative of your life how then
to begin to really grasp things like the
shadow or the animal or the self or any
number of these more minor archetypes as
well so that's one of the challenging
things it's the balance right it's both
the conceptual
and the feeling how do you how do you
did you do do you is it is it an
aspiration of yours to to what to
undergo that that personal work with
with people because I am how what do you
mean specifically I feel I feel often
when being truthful with people by
anything important there has to be a
trust there that that's actually what is
wanted that that's that we're willing to
go there together and if I can just tell
a story real quick I don't know this is
you know I'm a bit all over the place
but I'm coalescing something I've I feel
perhaps is it is interesting it relates
to the to what we've been speaking about
I once had an experience and I'll have
to leave out some details for privacy
but once had an experience I've had a
few like this I was talking to someone
who was on some LSD and maybe they had
taken a few other substances earlier in
a day or so I'm pretty sure LSD was the
main thing and I was sober but this you
know is after sort of a number of years
of exploration and and integration on my
part and there's a certain awareness I
can take up in relationship to someone
on these experiences I can sort of drop
into a bit of the shared resonation so
we were trapped we were tracking each
other very well
we were speaking about DMT we were
speaking about the relationship between
the DMT experience but also what occurs
in your life and again this link between
the inner world and the narrative of how
you are acting and how you are aware of
your relation embedded relationship with
others and what have you and a few other
things happen in a conversation it got
to a point where
I really like I felt like all this is
super interesting to me is very very
salient I was I was creatively like I
was moving towards my own frontier and I
stepped out a little bit and I said
something and then we were tracking each
other and he fainted he collapsed and he
hit the ground I'm quite hard and put
him into the recovery position he woke
up his friends were there he was okay
he had never had that happen before now
there's physiological things going on
and I'm not trying to make an argument
at this was because what I said
necessarily but we can if we extract
from this the idea that someone's cup
can be overfilled and there can be the
expression perhaps of a certain truth
that one is not ready for like for
example with a child when do you express
to them certain things about the nature
of the world when do we it's a it's
again the cultivation of what's
appropriate and so that and so I wonder
how how you feel like your own
development when do you know like when
do you feel when do you know it is
appropriate or you are ready to engage
in a certain kind of like genuinely
transformative reaction interaction
people can think of shamans right like
when are you ready to have to take on
that role and I feel like perhaps Pete a
lot of people step into that far far far
too soon so this is something that I for
sure probably don't do well it's kind of
known amongst my family in my friend
group like beware if you call Eric
because I don't do it on purpose but
like it's like there's this wolf in me
that can smell if there's a hi if
there's truth being hidden and it wants
to ask about this truth and if I'm not
if I'm not emotionally calm like if I
get anxious or angry that wolf will
force a conversation that probably is
not ready to be had mm-hmm and something
that a trained therapist will be taught
is you might be able to smell the
person's problem the first day you are
not
truth and love if you let them know on
the first day that their husband's
cheating on them or that their sons gay
or whatever it is like your your role is
to gently ask questions and slowly help
them be able to see it themselves yes
but there's also a part of that that I
don't like because a part of that feels
manipulative on my part like who am i hi
to choose whether or not you're ready
for this truth and so again it feels
like it comes down to this gut feeling
mm-hmm and truly the way to do this is
to not talk to someone like you're the
one in power and for it to be amongst
equals and both parties agree that we're
gonna be in our truth and if I ask you a
question for you to feel comfortable to
say my truth is right now I feel in my
body that I'm not ready to talk about
this and then and then we can move on
from that point I think the beautiful
thing about this sort of stuff is like
the real world does not have black and
white lines like the like human
experience between two humans is not a
black or white thing and so a lot of
this is feeling and the way we learn is
to do and we tend to fuck up and so like
you will learn by doing mm-hmm and
you'll just get a better and a better
sense of is this the place to say the
truth and love or is this the place to
just be and love just a hold space for
is this the space just to be quiet and
to make eye contact is this the space
just a hug you know is this the space to
make the a joke mm-hmm a thing that I
know that I have a hard time doing is I
have a hard time joking because I'm so
interested in only speaking the truth
that it kind of fucks with my ability to
make jokes and that's something that I
feel like I'm trying to work on and to
cultivate that's pretty funny right and
I'm just trying to find that balance
especially being in a relationship now
where I'm monogamous and I feel deeply
committed to one person
like it can be exhausting talking to
someone like me every day and so I'm
trying to find more ways to be playful
and to like be humorous and just to
bring some levity interactions because
imagine having a talk like this every
fucking day actually yeah yeah no I hear
you man as the the lightness the the
relate did you know the the levity and
the depth I have to go hand in hand or
you're out of balance I find I should
say I find I know I am when they are out
out of hand and yeah it's a it's a
beautiful thing it's a beautiful thing
to switch to switch between them
I enjoy relationships where there can be
such stark jumps from one to another
without yeah absolutely yeah without the
degradation of either one and if you
know in fact just coming to me there it
might be the case that if those jumps
aren't possible then actually there's
something there's something there maybe
inside you maybe inside there maybe
something unspoken be a million things
but there's something there that you've
triggered yourself somehow and you need
to attend to something actually a little
bit of an insecurity at least talking
from my own perspective of well it
wasn't quite ready for that it's funny
it's funny it links up with another you
know a bit of a tangent by a link start
with this idea of and the more one
cultivates awareness the more one takes
on responsibility and it's got there's a
link there between awareness and
responsibility right because all of a
sudden your containers bigger than to be
in a sort of loving truthful
relationship with it to be in a
relationship of integrity all of a
sudden means that you're your nodal
network is that much more salient it's
more developmental and so that
responsibility increases and with that
responsibility with that awareness there
comes
proportional distance to fall which is
an interesting one and maybe you had the
techniques to get back up once you fool
but but but I
but I find that responsibility only
continues to increase and I feel I feel
that's something important to bring to
the party as well look alright what time
is it
it's 655 for you we probably have
another 10 15 20 minutes I'm not usually
too good at too good at this part where
it's like shit there's a million things
I actually would be interested to talk
to you about I don't know I want to give
you the space to to close up anything
you feel like we haven't closed up just
from this little bit here but otherwise
I could ask the wait man yeah I could I
could ask you a couple different things
I've I'd say the main way I engage with
what you do over the last six seven
months is occasionally when I open
Instagram you'll be a boat there'll be a
post from you on there and you write you
write beautifully actually I would like
to say that I appreciate what you're
doing I know you've you probably
received that feedback quite a lot but
but as you should I feel like you
genuinely do offer you express your
truth there and I have no doubt
whatsoever that it's valuable to many
people and I appreciate it I see and I'm
like alright well done mate yeah fair
play yeah you can't leave a like that
and it's interesting right because
you're you're given a lot of your
personal development and your own story
throughout these things and there's a
certain vulnerability in this you've
also been taking a few psychedelics here
and there that have been important parts
of your your journey what can I ask you
about psychedelics I feel there's just
so much stuff to discuss have you has
been something in your psychedelic
experience where it's still in that box
of oh shit I don't know I don't know
about integrating this one that is like
what's going on there I've maybe bitten
into that like one two percent and it
has their business what what is that
thing for you how what are you if you
were to consider like just taking an
extra step forward into coalescing some
of the more profoundly novel experiences
you've had in any of your psychedelic
journeys what would come to mind the
hardest thing for me to grasp on a
psychedelic that I said I just I know
that I haven't integrated is there is
this feeling that whatever the truth of
reality is I will only be capable of
digesting it at the moment I die yeah
and there's this feeling that I know
that I am inside of the illusion that
I'm doing my best to be in my truth to
the best of my ability because that is
the way that I know or feel is the most
gracious way to be in the illusion but
that the immensity of whatever this
thing is I do not possess the power or
the ability to comprehend it but I feel
like at the moment of my death I will be
like oh so that's the biggest one from
psychedelics I don't count
edible marijuana as a psychedelic but my
worst trips my hardest trips come from
way too much of an edible and the ideas
that come from that that I just can't
shake then a part of me I and I I don't
know if it's my truth or if it's a fear
thing plain as truth but on psychedelics
I can see instantly come up against the
idea of you
are an illusion everything in your life
is an illusion and you're either in a
coma and you're making all this up or
you're in a simulation and this is just
simply not real but both of those feel
like my mind creating a story to justify
the fact that I feel disoriented from
how high I am and my mind automatically
generates the most intense story to
justify why I feel the amount of fear
that I feel yeah oh because ultimately
my my metaphysical question is always if
so then what and if either of those are
real and I can't do anything so I'm just
gonna live my life I'm gonna be in truth
I'm gonna try to love people I'm gonna
try to be of service to the world I'm
gonna try to help I'm gonna have orgasms
and eat good food hmm yeah beautiful me
the questioning process is is but the
participation in the transformative
cycle it is our the inquiry
it's that revolution between stepping
into novelty and the integration of it
attachment and detachment it's like
simulation or not I mean it is a
simulation but we participate in a
simulation the reality is the process of
transformation and it's there's that's
that's that's a light as anything and
deep as all hell at the same time that
first comment you made about their
apprehension only possible on death hmm
it's interesting right because death is
often used metaphorically it's like
death and rebirth fucking death and
rebirth this dynast I'm talking about
myself a death and rebirth that and it's
like yeah death of
some sort of narrative particular map of
coherence particular framework of
fixation and then the the re-imagination
and the recapturing of another frame
that rebirth again and what is that
there's that there's something about
that like like the real deal like that
the physical death - I mean I it's like
hmm
how much I mean let's talk about
psychedelics and spiritual practice and
philosophy even being a preparation for
death and it seems to me it is it seems
to me that but you can only say maybe
and it's only a seeming that we touch
death in transformation but at that
point it is a it's not something that
can be referred to as as a death is not
it's not it's not something which
permits any referential points it's a
being with it's an immersion with its
you know where the emptiness where the
void whether Christ consciousness you
know whether whatever whatever the
language wherever the language it's a
however acceptance surrender what it's
not it's not it's not capture war in any
reference and there's a sense of them
maybe there's a way to cultivate and
moving into that space where that kind
of that's sort of that expression you
did with a kind of like the the mouth
opening into the or is is a release of
the need to grasp a release of the need
to fix finally and it's just on that
occasion we don't find we ain't coming
back from it and at that we are just
referring to some sort of you know like
what sort of image the soul leaving the
world but it's like we only have
psychological images to make sense
and we don't get outside of it and in
this sense we are just though we are a
fragmentary source of divinity but we
are not the God outside of things we are
not outside of we are very much a part
of and engaging in these processes of
transformation and but but but to say
all this as well it's like I do my best
to check in and be honest but but even
this of course is just language course
is just expression mad fucking shingles
I was still I'm coming off the end of
having shingles which is like an adult
version of chickenpox and I had them
around the back of my back through my
thigh like right up alongside my balls
which is particularly interesting
because it seemed like to stimulate the
exact nerve that is stimulated when you
get kicked in the balls
so Felicity like 72 hours I was getting
kicked in the balls everything 30
seconds kind of like alright this is the
reality now I just accept it and I'm in
this other place I don't know where I'm
going with that exactly but it's like I
don't know like what do we have the
power like what what is people can hold
so much we are so capable of of
acceptance like a radical acceptance of
the conditions of life yet still somehow
the trajectory towards love the
trajectory towards acceptance and being
available as you are and an acceptance
of the quality of the potential of the
beauty of things remains and this is
such a remarkable is the kind of thing
that you know it's it's it's it's
tear-jerking it's so incredible that
that people have the capacity to do
these things and we we and we all have
we all have mountains to climb and then
we all deal with the precipice and then
sometimes we're floating down the river
and that's movie that's maybe the best
part of it but man sometimes it's not so
much of a float sometimes it's like fuck
me I just got swooped on by an eagle as
I smashed into a log bulls first but
amen yeah man Eric thank you for doing
this and stay in patient with me we took
maybe three to four months to get here
having this with each other
worth it absolutely worth it and the
thing is it would have been it would
have been a little bit different every
time my life has taken so many shifts
and bits of development and some some
really challenging dark moments and then
also the rebirth from them and I feel
like I feel like this this came exactly
as it should
is there anything is there anything
you'd like to express as we sort of move
towards closing here just my gratitude
for you having me on and holding a space
where you have I can tell that you were
incredibly present for this and I
appreciate it
mmm yeah beautiful man I appreciate you
too so your latest podcast is the Miss
that make us yes sir yeah which I'll
have a link to everywhere this appears I
thoroughly recommend checking that out
it's an investigation into it's an
extrapolation of your guest story and
the narratives that comprise their lives
most meaningfully which is a beautiful
which is a beautiful idea for a podcast
thank you brother yeah